We're halfway there-ish.
Well, we've covered first normal
form and some of the rules,
determinants and functional dependencies.
And now second normal form. So
as a reminder, it has to be in
first normal form. If it's not, we
stop and we fix the first normal
form. But if it is, here, if I had
a flash card, I don't have a flash
card, I just have a plain card.
Yep,
not a heart, but I have this. If
it were a flash card, though, I
would put down second normal form
and the word partial dependencies.
So second normal form is a
partial dependency. And what that
means, technically, is each column
must depend on the whole key.
Well, what's the whole key?
The whole key is a composite
primary key. This is the key, and
there's two columns to the key.
So when you're thinking about
second normal form, this is the
craziest thing on the test. If
it's not a composite primary,
it can't violate second normal form.
Now, if it violates first normal
form, of course it violates second
normal form, but that's more of
a technicality, right? You'd fix
the first normal form and then go
on. But if you don't have a composite
primary here, second normal form
is fine because it's the whole
key, meaning that these non-keys
have to depend on the entire key.
Let's take a look at this. Project name.
I have to know the project
number and the employee
number to determine project
name, true or false.
The more I look at this, I
start to think, what does
the employee number have to
do with the project name?
Let's look at the second
or the last column, though.
Project number, employee number
to determine the hours, okay?
And this is why in the exam
everything's A, B, N, O, P,
because here you have to
think through it going, okay,
what happens if employee works
on more than one project?
If that's the case, you
would have to establish which
project that they're working
on. So to determine the number
of hours you would need, I'm
on project one, I'm employee
number two, and on that
project I worked five hours.
So maybe Joseph worked for five
hours on data 3330 grading.
But then Joseph worked
for four more hours here
on a different project, 4330.
So we need both the project
and the employee to assign.
But this one's still
problematic, project name.
I just have to know the
project number to determine the
project name, because if it's
project one, it's always going
to be blue square. If it's
project two, it's always going
to be four corners. It's like
building ID. Building ID one,
Eccles Center. Building ID two,
Huntsman Hall. Building ID
three, the new learning center,
the Garner Learning Center.
So in every case, we just
need part of the key to
determine the project name.
That would be an example of
a second normal form problem.
Oh, there's the arrow.
Project number alone determines
project name. Here's another example.
Must be in first normal form, no
partial dependencies, blah, blah,
all that, right? So now we have
student ID, activity ID, activity fee.
Again, what does the activity fee have
to do with the student. In this case,
activity ID 2 is $10.
Activity ID 2 is $10.
Activity ID 4 is $20.
So in this case, we know that part
of the key, activity ID, determines
activity fee. And think back of
the unintended consequences because
in this case, if I have to change
the activity fee, I just want to
change it one place. Where in here,
in this particular design, I have
to change it a bunch of places.
And if I change it here to $12 and
I leave this one here at $10. Now
I have just a database that doesn't
have reliable data. That's part
of the reason we do this whole
normalization process, how we divide
tables out. So here's the fix. The
nice thing is the fix for second
normal form is the same as the fix for
third normal form. It's just a
different problem that we're fixing.
So here it is in the ABNOP,
how you'll see it on the exam.
We have a composite primary.
So immediately I would think
that's possibly violating
second normal form. Not always.
B determines P.
Part of the key determines a
non-key. So that is a second
normal form problem. Part
of the key, non-key, second
normal form, or from the flash
card, partial dependency,
right? Partial dependency,
second normal form problem.
Here's how we fix it.
The determinant that causes the problem
becomes the primary key of the new table.
That's why being able to write
determinants and functional
dependencies is so important. It
creates a simple formula. And for
those who have taken calculus,
for those who have taken math 1001
or something, the lowest math,
this is far easier. It's just
different than what you're used
to. So in this case, B becomes the
new primary key, so it's underlined.
And I call P, the non-key
here, the tag along. It tags
along with P to create this table.
Now, in the original table, you
don't really change anything.
So if you have a primary
composite, you leave it. If B is
underlined like it is, you
leave it. But you do make two
changes. Number one is the primary
key in the new table becomes
the foreign key in the original
table, meaning the original
table is the child table. I'll
talk about that in a minute.
But B is italicized,
meaning this is the foreign
key. This is how these
tables will link up.
And then P is deleted from
the original table because
it's here now and we have
to gain that efficiency. So
we don't have to write that
every time we add a new
row to the database. So now we
have A, B, B is italicized, N and O
in the original table, and then B
underlined and P. And how we know
it's the child table? One, that's
where the italics is. So this
is the child table. What this means
is you have to exist here. So B
in this, excuse me, B in the
original table must first exist and
be in the new table. So this is
like a student table perhaps or a
course table and this is more of
a class setup where this is your
grade and this is the last day attended
or something. But it's a little
bit strange when you create or
fix normalization. The new table
you create is the parent table.
Here's another one. We have A, B,
N, O, P. We know that A and B
are a composite primary so it's
possibly violating second normal
form. we're given this information
that a determines n now what that
is doesn't matter this could be
project id determines project
name or something but it's much
easier here where we can look
at it more of a math problem
or a simple math problem where
a determines n then we have a
problem so a is part of the key
determines n that's a second
normal form problem or a partial
dependency part of the key.
Again, the fix, exactly the same. The
determinant becomes the primary key.
N is the tag along.
In the original table, we simply
italicize. I need to italicize
A. I can't tell if it is,
or I could just put FK here.
B, and then in the original
table, N needs to be deleted,
this is wrong, and then O stays
there. So this is a typo here.
A would be italicized
and N would be deleted.
I'm just going to leave
this on the screen.
These are the actual steps as you
go through the process that I just
described, but sometimes it's easier
to see the example than read the
step-by-step description of it,
but you can certainly read through
that second normal form fixed, but
I would recommend if you need more
practice going back and looking at
the examples. Third normal form.
As a reminder, third normal
form must be in second
normal form, and second
normal form must be in first
normal form. So now we're
looking at third normal form.
Third normal form is no transitive
dependencies. And remember
our review sheet, we had a key
and a non-key. So transitive
dependency is just a non-key
can determine another non-key.
So for instance, we have employee number.
This looks great. And then we
have the employee's last name.
If I know the employee number,
I would know their last name. I
would know their job class. I
would know their hourly charge.
And again, where that's
confusing, just ask yourself, if
I know employee number one,
what's the hourly charge? $50.
If I know employee one,
what's the job class?
Job class is one.
So we know that. But
then we start to look
for, does a non-key
determine another non-key?
Again, this is the reason we use the
letters because you don't have to
spend an hour thinking about if I
know our last name, do I really know
job class? Or if I know job class,
do I really know the hourly charge?
But you can see in this case, if I
know job class one, it's 50 bucks.
Job class two, 60 bucks. We assume
this is the population, although
as a real world database person,
you would have to consider what the
possibilities in the future would
be. But this is a level three normal
form transitive problem where job
class determines hourly wage. And
yes, hourly wage determines job class,
but you would typically take the
numeric value that could be an ID
and then the actual value. So in
this particular case, we know that
job class determines hourly charge.
And there's the arrow again.
I keep forgetting the arrow.
So here's another example. We
have the employee ID. We have the
receipt number and we have the
store name and the store number.
We do know if it's store 100,
it's Joe's. And if it's store
101, it's Moe's. So here we
have a non-key determining
another non-key. So this would
violate third normal form.
Fixing second and third
normal form again,
same thing, just a different problem.
A, B, N, O, P, O, and as a reminder, key,
composite key, non-key, non-key, non-key.
Now we have a non-key
determining a non-key.
That is a third normal form
problem, non-key, non-key. The fix
as a reminder, this will become
the primary key. this will become
the tag-along, this will be
italicized, this will be deleted.
So in the new table, yep,
this is the primary key,
this is the tag-along
in the original table.
So now you have a fully
normalized two tables.
This would be the parent, this would
be the child, it's the child because
the foreign key is in the original
table, the way we fixed the design.
And again, here are the specific step
-by-step fixes to the third normal
form. Here are a few more examples.
If you look at it, you can pause
the screen too if you want to take
a guess, but in this case, three,
two, one, we have a composite primary
and determines O. That's a non-key
to a non-key. This would be an example
of a third normal form problem.
The new table, primary key, tag along,
and the old table, N is
italicized and O is out of there.
In this case, we have a composite,
so it could be a problem.
We don't know for sure. We
have order ID and item ID,
and we have item name and quantity.
So if we look at item ID,
and sometimes it's item name,
right, based on the item ID. So
we do know if it's 50, it's Diet
Coke. If it's 20, it's milk.
50 Diet Coke and 60 potato.
Well, it works out that part of
the key determines a non-key.
so here we have a second normal
form problem and we would fix
it item ID the primary key of
the new table item name is to tag
along in the original table here
we italicize item ID we still
leave it composite and then we
get rid of the item name and
later we can link those up oh I
do want to show one more example
before we go to the animation
here's an exam here's another
example of data that we can
look at this one is set up with
the primary key student ID
and then we have sibling one,
sibling two, and sibling three.
So in this case, it looks like,
as far as we know, student
ID one has at least three,
student ID three has two siblings,
student ID two though doesn't have
any, so these will be null values.
This is an example of a repeating
group where we're trying to guess
how many siblings they have.
This would be a first normal form
violation based on the primary key
is there, the data types look okay,
one piece of information per cell,
but we have this repeating group
where we're trying to force guessing
how many possible siblings they
may have. They may have too many
siblings to fit or we might have
too many null values but either
way this would violate first normal
form. I'm so excited to show you
your first animation. The goal of
the animations is longer term
retention and as you watch a cartoon
or a video you tend to remember
it differently especially if it's
complemented by a presentation and
examples in a lab so now we have
the demonstration we have the
animation and then you'll have the lab
all with a goal of longer term
retention and defeating that forgetting
curve of ebbing house so i hope
you enjoy it and i hope you
learn a ton from it it'll first
review first one through three normal
forms and then introduce you to
a boyce cod normal form welcome
back to are you normalized
our final contestant is tina
tables from dataville university hi
everyone i'd like to give a shout
out to my 33 30 classmates and my
favorite professor dr kelly that's
very nice but i didn't approve
that shout out so we'll deduct a
couple of points right off the bat
all right let's get
normalized all right tina
here's your final table
design this table consists
of three columns course
professor and textbook
as you can see course
and professor are both
underlined are you ready
tina i'm ready freddy
Who's Freddy? Is he a new player?
Didn't authorize that either.
Anyways, let's get started.
Tina, is this table in
first normal form or not?
Let's see. I use the DROP drop acronym
to determine first normal form.
The D stands for data
types are consistent.
R, no repeating groups.
O, one piece of information per cell.
And P, primary key is established.
Just to pause for a minute, too,
I forgot to mention on data types,
they do have to be consistent.
So I mentioned all character,
all numeric. There was an example
earlier, I think, of a serial
number that was alphanumeric. And so
in this case, we probably wouldn't
list it like this. and that's
explained later in the video, but
if we used an alphanumeric SQL 101,
if that is the textbook title,
then it would be okay. Data 101,
again, it's not ideal, but we
would probably have something like
a CRN, but in terms of alphanumeric.
So does this violate first
normal form? You could probably
argue that it does, but in this case,
we're just assuming that these
are intended to should be that way
in terms of atomic value and in
terms of data type consistency.
In this case, I can only determine that
a primary key has been established.
We have a composite
primary key with course and
professor. So yes, it's
in first normal form.
You got it.
round two is the table in second
normal form we have a composite
primary key so it's possible to have
a partial dependency or second normal
form violation however in this
case course alone doesn't determine
the textbook and professor alone
doesn't determine the textbook it?
Yes, it's in second normal
form. Absolutely correct.
Round three.
Is the table in third
normal form? Third normal
form requires no transitive dependencies.
No non-key can determine in
another non-key. There is
only one non-key. The table
is in third normal form.
Well, I've determined
that you are correct.
Yippee, I did it. I win, right? Where are
the streamers? Where's the grand prize?
Calm down, Tina, or we will
call security. All right.
there is one final question for
the grand prize this one's a
hard one is every determinant a
candidate key of course wait what
it's an important concept in
normalization everyone should know
this one is every determinant
a candidate key yes in this
table every Every determinant is
a candidate key? Ooh, I'm sorry,
Tina. In this table, every
determinant is not a candidate key.
Look closely at the columns
textbook and course.
Well, based on the data,
a textbook does determine
course, but I thought third
normal form was all there was.
A common mistake.
Typically, third normal
form is sufficient. However,
on very rare occasions,
normalization problems persist.
This table violates Boyce-Codd
Normal Form, or BCNF for short.
That said, BCNF doesn't occur very
often, and it wasn't included in
the original paper on normalization.
However, in our sample table,
we have a non-key attribute textbook
that determines part of... And in
a regular data set, this probably
isn't realistic. However, if you
look at the data in the example,
SQL 101 is data 101 in every case.
TSQL 102 in every case is data 101.
SQL 201 is always the 2000 or 200
level. And so if this were the
data, then yes, it does violate
BoyceCodd normal form. Now, for us,
we use, for instance, TSQL been
gone for both the 3330 and 4330.
So in that particular instance,
it wouldn't. But this example, it
does, where a non-key determines
part of a key. And that, by
definition, is Boyce-Codd normal
form. Composite primary key course.
That's what we call a BCNF problem.
Oh, I see. With textbook
determining course, then not
all determinants are candidate
keys, even though the
table is in the first,
second, and third normal form.
Textbook determines
part of the primary key.
Exactly. That's BCNF for ya.
Let's fix the BCNF problem.
First, we create a new table with
textbook as the primary key and course
as the non-key attribute. Then we
remove the course column from the
original table and make textbook the
foreign key link to the new table.
In the original table, we make
professor and textbook composite
primary keys. Now every determinant
is a key. BCNF clean. Wait,
this is a fix? That
design looks terrible.
The design is in BCNF.
Even though you're squeaky
clean in BCNF, this
whole design would be
better with a surrogate key.
This is how I fixed the BCNF
problem that we looked at.
There are probably other
fixes, but for this
class 3330, all you'll
have to do is recognize a
BCNF problem. You won't
have to fix the problem.
The idea of BCNF was so rare
that in the original paper, I
think it was mentioned, but
they didn't find the BCNF. It's
almost a theoretical or
academic problem to create, but
in terms of the layout, this
is much more of the layout that
you would likely have with a
class theme, a course theme,
textbook course theme, which is
where you can put some together, and
then a professor ID. So this is the
layout that I have but again beyond
the scope fixing BCNF problem just
understand non key part of the key
Sometimes the best key isn't natural
at all. It's a surrogate one column
Identity one comma one
Simple joins no messy composites and your
functional dependencies stay clear. Wow
I guess normalization gets
you far, but design is about
clarity, and sometimes the
real winner is a surrogate key.
So did I win the grand prize?
Absolutely.
The grand prize is knowledge.
Congratulations, Tina.
All right. Hope you enjoyed
and learned from the video.
This is just an academic example
of BCNF. So BCNF must be in third
normal form, third must be in
second, second must be in first.
And the rule is, this is the
ultimate rule, and it does
apply to the second, third
normal form, but ultimately to
this Boyce-Codd. All determinants
must be candidate keys.
For our class, it will always be
a composite primary key. And the
example of a BCNF is, if you look at
this in terms of first normal form,
we know that AB is underlined, so
all we can really tell, and we don't
have the repeating groups is this is
in first normal form. Second normal
form is when part of the key
determines a non-key. So that's fine.
Third normal form is when a non
-key determines a non-key and that's
okay. And then we get the weirdo,
right? D determines B. A non
-key determines part of a key.
So that by definition is a BCNF.
Again, it's hard to even
come up with examples and
the examples generally
wouldn't hold over long-term.
But in this particular
case, we can see that D,
well, as an example, I guess we
have a composite, but Corcoran,
as far as we know, Corcoran teaches
math, and right now math is only
taught by Corcoran. That's not
true, though, because Fidel also
teaches math. However, in this
case, Corcoran only teaches math,
Heinz only teaches psychology,
and Fidel only teaches
math. So if this were the
population, We have a non-key
determining part of a key.
That would be an example of a
BCNF normal form problem. So all
you'll have to do in class is to
identify it when you have part
of a key determining another
non-key. The solution, again, is
something we almost start over,
at least the way I approach it,
as opposed to trying to build
off of what we have originally.
Here's another example of how
it would show up on the exam.
We have the original table, A,
B composite, D, P are non-keys.
If we don't get anything
else, we know that it's
fine, but we get this one
extra piece of information.
It says D determines B, so in
that case, we have a part of
a key. We have a non-key
determining part of a key, so that
would be a B, C, and F
normalization. So here's the review.
First normal form is the
atomic drop. Data types
are consistent, no repeating
groups, one piece of
information per cell, and
a primary key established.
Two, no partial dependencies, part
of the key determining a non-key.
Three, transitive dependencies,
a non-key determining a
non-key. And then this is
BCNF, you need to change that,
is a non-key determines
part of a key. Fourth normal
form is something completely
different outside of
the scope of class. That's
multi-valued dependencies.
So here's the review, I'll change
that fourth to third, or to BCNF.
And ultimately, the ultimate is all
determinants are candidate keys.
We'll see you next time.